In this work,
We proposed a vision-based decentralized relative
pose-estimation architecture based on GNNs.
Our key idea is the implicit virtual leader (IVL),
a non-physical formation reference frame implicitly
learned by the neural network from monocular images
and inter robot communication.
Relying solely on visual input,
our network achieves relative-pose based formation control
without the need for any additional localization sensors.
In our network architecture,
all robots operate as equal peers without a centralized hierarchy
powered by decentralized edge inference.
This enables zero latency, dynamic switching of the leader at any time.
If any robot goes offline,
the remaining peer seamlessly maintain the formation.
This eliminates the single-point-of-failure inherent
in traditional leader-follower modes,
significantly boosting system reliability.
Trained just once,
our network can deployed across heterogeneous robots,
such as wheeled and quadruped robots,
enabling zero-shot deployment.
Even in the absence of visual overlap,
our architecture maintains highly accurate relative pose estimation.
When encountering obstacles,
our network outputs reliable uncertainty estimation to guarantee formation safety.
In this experiment,
The blue RoboMaster automatically stops due to high uncertainty，
while the other two adapt into a two-robot formation.
Once the obstacle is removed,
the re-online blue robot automatically resumes the collaborative formation.
To validate the pose estimation accuracy，
we demonstrate heterogeneous multi-robot formation switching through a narrow tunnel.
With a tunnel width of only about 3 RoboMaster widths (0.72m),
our method delivers a success rate close to 100%.
Lastly, we demonstrate a 5-robot formation with low latency.
In the future, we plan to extend this framework to achieve
more complex multi-robot obstacle avoidance, planning and navigation,
empowering multi-robot systems with ultimate resilience
and seamless, cross-platform adaptability.